E. Thomas Billard Papers
E. Thomas Billard Papers
1969-1978
Billard, E. Thomas.
2 linear ft.
Papers of a Syracuse University MBA graduate and Vietnam War veteran. Collection includes correspondence and audio cassette recordings.
4788419
Biographical History
Edmund Thomas Billard (1946- ) is a former American military officer, a native of McLean, New York and a 1981 MBA graduate from Syracuse University. He was born in Catskill, NY.
Following his graduation from Cornell University in June 1968, Billard enlisted in the Army in July 1968. He attended Basic and Advanced Infantry Training at Fort Dix, New Jersey and then Engineer Officer Candidate School (OCS) at Fort Belvoir, Virginia. Following completion of the Engineer OCS course in June 1969, he received a commission in Military Intelligence and was assigned to the Army Security Agency. He served with the 82nd Airborne Division at Fort Bragg, North Carolina and volunteered to go to Vietnam, where he served from August 1970 to May 1971. While serving in Vietnam, Billard, in addition to writing traditional letters, sent a number of voice tapes recording his observations and travels during his tour of duty. Following the completion of his military service commitment, Billard left the Army in May 1971.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The E. Thomas Billard Papers includes audio cassette recordings, correspondence, photographs and other memorabilia from Billard's service in Vietnam and in the years immediately following.
Correspondence includes both written letters and audio recordings between Billard and his family in Upstate New York.
Memorabilia includes photographs and slides. Most are from Billard's tour in Vietnam but some are from trips to Thailand and Germany. The slides were received in two carousel boxes; one of these contained a loaded carousel, the other contained individual slides, some in smaller boxes as they would have come from the developer, others loose in the box. There is also a 25th Infantry military yearbook.
Miscellaneous includes military documents relating to Billard's service.
Other Formats Available
Many of the audiorecordings have been digitized and are available via, in the E. Thomas Billard Papers collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence tapes are arranged chronologically. Other material is alphabetical by type or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Military history; Billard, E. Thomas.; United States. -- Army. -- Infantry Division, 25th.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Soldiers' writings, American.; Germany.; Thailand.; Vietnam.; Ho Chi Minh City (Vietnam); Australia, Southeastern.; Upstate New York (N.Y.); Audiocassettes.; Correspondence.; Military records.; Paper money.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Sound recordings.; Yearbooks.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed off site and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of E. Thomas Billard, 2015, 2020.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  Most original envelopes have been removed and replaced with redacted copies.
  - Written letters
    - [General], 20 Mar-26 Dec 1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - [General], 4 Jan-16 Apr 1971; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Audio letters
    Many of the audiorecordings have been digitized and are available via, in the E. Thomas Billard Papers collection. More detailed contents notes were taken during digitization. In some instances, the audio engineers were able to recover content thought to be deleted, as many of the audio cassettes were used more than once. Tapes are arranged chronologically, as best as possible. Some of the tapes evidently accompany some of the slides (see Memorabilia: Slides) but the connection has been lost as to which slides they go with.
    - [Audio letter from family], 3-4 Oct 1970; billard_e_001; birthday parties and family gatherings; travel in Upstate New York; local events; Cornell football; weather; questions from family about Vietnam; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], 10-15 Oct 1970; billard_e_002; local events; Cornell football on WHCU; Billard to family on impressions of Vietnam; family time at the lake house with the Henrietta Billards (Tom’s brother’s family: John, Judy, Jimmy, Susan); Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], 17 Oct-1 Nov 1970; billard_e_003; family response to "Vietnam problems and resolution"; Billard's possible return; local events; weather; activities of John (brother) and Peter (brother); Australian troops in Vietnam; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - Tape #1, 5 Nov 1970; billard_e_033; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Tape #2, 5 Nov 1970; billard_e_034; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 8-19 Nov 1970; billard_e_021; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 3)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 15 Nov [1970]; billard_e_022; note on cassette case reads: "Tom - this tape has a message on it"; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 21-23 Nov 1970; billard_e_004; Cornell football on WHCU; weather; Syracuse football; weather in Vietnam; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], 27-29 Nov 1970; billard_e_005; ristmas lists; Thanksgiving celebration; weather; music preferences; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - The Classical Guitar #2, 4 Dec 1970; billard_e_006; classical guitar selections (dubbed from LP); Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Saigon, etc. Sides 1 and 2 copy, 10-17 Dec 1970; billard_e_007; from Billard to family; trip to Saigon; Billard's general responsibilities; Billard's travel and observations; training; weather in Vietnam; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Saigon, etc. Sides 3 and 4 copy, 10-17 Dec 1970; billard_e_008; from Billard to family; "Sunrise in Saigon" Radio; sending home souvenirs; American Forces Vietnam Radio; Nixon and the 1972 campaign; Trip to Australia; Sports; Christmas; observations of local dress and buildings; Saigon weather; Bien Hoa Air base; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Saigon, etc. [marked original tape in new case], [10-17 Dec 1970]; billard_e_010; from Billard to family; more on travels in Saigon and region; observations on work and the war; Billard's return; Long Binh Ward; weather; William Calley's Court Martial; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Saigon, etc (transferred to another tape) [empty case], 10-17 Dec 1970; billard_e_023; most likely this is the case for billard_e_010 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 13-15 Dec 1970; billard_e_009; Christmas Party; reading from magazines; local events; weather; call from Billard on Christmas Day?; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], [Dec 1970]; billard_e_018; Christmas and family celebrations; personal updates on family members. Recovered audio from Billard to Family with Christmas greetings and personal messages; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 24-25 Dec 1970; billard_e_024; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Christmas Day 1970, 25 Dec 1970; billard_e_011; from family; local weather and events; local radio; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 26-31 Dec 1970; billard_e_025; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 3-5 Jan 1970 [1971]; billard_e_012; personal comments; veterans events in Cortland; local weather; Nixon; WHCU local radio; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], 10-21 Jan 1971; billard_e_013; holiday and birthday celebrations; WHCU radio; local events; weather; comments on slides Billard sent to family; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 21-27 Jan 1970 [1971]; billard_e_026; date on cassette is 1970 but most likely this should be 1971, as Billard served in Vietnam from August 1970 to May 1971; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 25 Jan 1971; billard_e_014; children playing; Bill Cosby on Radio/TV; aftermath of winter storm; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 30-31 Jan 1971; billard_e_027; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Slides: Trip to Tay Ninh, 2 Feb 1971; billard_e_035; slides 58-77; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Slides: Long Bihn Depot 51-66; 372nd St. D, Slide Program 1, 3-4 Feb 1971; billard_e_036; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 13-26 Feb 1971; billard_e_028; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 3)
    - Twelve Days at Xuan Loc; Trip to Xuan Loc, Slides, 19 Feb 1971; billard_e_037; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 3)
    - Program #4: Ben Luc, Saigon, 20 Feb 1971; billard_e_038; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Program #3: Trip to Ben Luc, Saigon; Trip to Con Son, 21 Feb 1971; billard_e_039; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 28 Feb-4 March1971; billard_e_029; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Program #5: Xuan Loc, 3-18 Mar 1971; billard_e_040; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 4-5 Mar 1971; billard_e_015; weather - blizzard; school closings; more comments on slides; WHCU radio; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes: Blizzard; Good News!, 5-15 Mar 1971; billard_e_030; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Program #6, 18 Mar 1971; billard_e_041; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - Program #7, 18 Mar 1971; billard_e_042; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], 21-23 Mar 1971; billard_e_016; comments on weather; Billard's trip to Australia; local real estate market; family birthdays; WHCU radio; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Australia #1 and #2, 28-30 Mar 1971; billard_e_031; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 3)
    - Australia #3 and #4, 30 Mar-2 Apr 1971; billard_e_017; from Billard to family; his trip to Australia; weather and local geography; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam Tapes, 15-20 Apr 1971; billard_e_032; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 3)
    - [Audio letter from family], billard_e_019; plans for after Billard's return; personal relationships; Audio cassette; running time 30 (Box 2)
    - [Audio letter from family], billard_e_020; local events; family events; personal relationships; weather; civilian jobs; war in Middle East; Audio cassette; running time 60 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs, Mar-Apr 1970 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, [1970-1971]; note reads "8 pictures described on tape 2/19/71 side 2 approx 1/4 to 1/3"; this is probably billard_e_037 (Box 4)
  - Slides [carousel], 1970-1971; originally in carousel; removed, sleeved, order retained; notes on outside of box indicate that one of the tapes has narration to accompany (Box 4)
  - Slides, Family, 1969; 1975-1976,; undated (Box 4)
  - Slides, Germany trip, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Slides, Thailand, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Slides, [illegible], 1969; 1971; originally in small box, with enclosed handwritten slip of paper (Box 4)
  - Slides, [illegible], 1976; originally in small box, with enclosed handwritten slip of paper (Box 4)
  - Slides, miscellaneous, 1969-1975; received loose in second carousel box with no identifying information; arranged chronologically; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Slides, miscellaneous information, handwritten slips of paper found loose in box; notes from outside of second carousel box (Box 4)
  - Yearbook, "25th Infantry Division in Viet Nam, 1966-1967", includes luggage tags from military transport, Vietnamese and Thai paper money, found tucked inside front cover (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 6 Nov 1969-9 Jun 1971; address notification from Fort Benning (Georgia), letter concerning "Transfers Between Reserve Groups or Units," post stamps (Box 1)